Guide to the Jay and Si-Lan Chen Leyda Papers TAM.083
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Jay and Si-Lan Chen Leyda Papers -
1913-1988
1930-1980
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Leyda, Jay, 1910-1988
Leyda, Si-lan Chen
TAM.083
17.5 Linear Feet in 33 manuscript boxes, 1 oversize flat box, and 2 folders
Jay Leyda (1910-1988) was a leading film historian, filmmaker, photographer, archivist, translator, teacher, and noted Sergei Eisenstein, Emily Dickinson and Herman Melville scholar. Leyda studied directing with Sergei Eisenstein at the Moscow State Film School, became a correspondent for Theatre Arts Monthly and New Theatre, and was an art critic for the Moscow News. In 1936, Leyda was the assistant to Iris Barry, curator of the Film Library of the Museum of Modern Art, but resigned amidst allegations that he was a subversive agent. Leyda went to Hollywood in 1942 where he was a technical advisor on films on Russian subjects and began work on Herman Melville documents which led to a number of books on the subject. In 1973, Leyda became professor of Cinema Studies at NYU. He died in 1988. His wife, Si Lan Chen Leyda (1909- ), was a modern dancer who pioneered the use of Chinese dance elements. Si-Lan Chen was born in Trinidad and attended the Bolshoi Ballet School and Vera Maya's school in Moscow where she met and married Leyda. Throughout the late 1930s and early 1940s, she toured and worked in Hollywood as a choreographer and dance instructor, and occasionally appeared in films. The collection includes their biographical material, correspondence, writings, and material pertaining to their various pursuits.
Sponsor Note
Processing was generously supported by the Estate of Jay Leyda (Elena Pinto Simon, Executrix).
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Donated by Jay Leyda in 1980 and 1988. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1980.004 and 1980.007. Additional donations of photographic materials in the early 2000s.
An accretion of correpondence was donated in September 2016. The provenance of this material is unknown. The accession number associated with this gift is 2016.058.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Historical/Biographical Note
Jay Leyda (1910-1988) was a leading film historian, best known for his work on Soviet cinema and director Sergei Eisenstein, and on Chinese cinema. He was also a film maker, photographer, archivist, translator, professor of cinema studies at New York University, and was also noted for his Emily Dickinson and Herman Melville scholarship. His wife, Si Lan Chen Leyda (1909- ) was a modern dancer who pioneered the use of Chinese dance elements.
Jay Leyda was born on February 12, 1910 in Detroit, Michigan, and was adopted and raised by his grandmother in Dayton, Ohio, after his mother's early divorce. In 1930 Jay moved to New York City to work for photographer Ralph Steiner. Leyda was published in Arts Weekly, exhibited at the Julien Levy gallery, worked for the Workers Film and Photo League, was a founding member of the Film Society and the Film Forum, and arranged music to be played during silent films. At this time he formed a liaison with the activist attorney Carol King and may have joined the Communist Party USA. In 1932 Leyda made his first film A Bronx Morning, which led to his September 1933 acceptance to the Moscow State Film School, where he studied directing with Sergei Eisenstein. Leyda became a correspondent for Theatre Arts Monthly and New Theatre, and using the pen name James Lincoln, was an art critic for the Moscow News. In 1934 Leyda married Si Lan Chen, whose sister Yolanda worked as a camera operator for Mosfilms. In 1934-35 Leyda worked for Eisenstein as photographer and archivist during the making of Bezhin Meadow.
In 1936 the Museum of Modern Art offered Leyda the position of Assistant Curator of Films, and he brought to New York a rare print of Potemkin and other films collected throughout Europe. Leyda expanded MOMA's film collection and wrote pamphlets on the history of film. A 1940 newspaper article alleged he was a subversive agent and his resignation was requested. In 1941 Eisenstein commissioned Leyda to translate and edit a group of essays which became The Film Sense(1942). Leyda moved to Hollywood in 1942 where he was a technical advisor on films on Russian subjects, including Mission to Moscow. At this time Leyda began his work on Herman Melville documents (planned as a birthday present for Eisenstein) which led to The Melville Log: a documentary life of Herman Melville(1951), as well as the Complete Stories of Melville(1949) and the Portable Melville(1952). In 1943 he was drafted into the Army but was discharged shortly thereafter. A translation project begun at this time was The Musorgsky Reader, a 1947 collaboration with Sergei Bertensson, with whom Leyda later co-authored Sergei Rachmaninoff: A Lifetime in Music, (1956). Highlights of Leyda's continuing work on Soviet cinema include Film Form: Essays in Film Theory(1949), his 1954 study film from the negative of Eisenstein's unfinished Que Viva Mexico, Kino, a History of the Russian and Soviet film(1960), and Eisenstein at Work(1980).
In 1954 Leyda left Los Angeles and for the next twenty years traveled widely, living abroad much of the time with London as a home base. From 1959-1964, Leyda spent much of his time in Peking at the China Film Archive, resulting in Dianying (Electric Shadows): an Account of Films and the Film Audience in China(1972). From 1964-1969, Leyda spent much of his time working at the Staatliches Filmarchiv in East Berlin in the German Democratic Republic, and in 1964 he published his Films Beget Films: a Study of the Compilation Film. Non-film undertakings included The Years and Hours of Emily Dickinson(1960), and the 1964 performance of the opera Bartelby the Scrivener, for which Leyda wrote the libretto. In 1973, after brief teaching jobs at Yale and York Universities, Leyda became professor of Cinema Studies at NYU. He published Voices of Film Experience: 1894-to the Present(1977), regularly visited the USSR and published several collections of Eisenstein materials, and continued to write, lecture, curate, and consult widely on film and other topics. Leyda died on February 15, 1988.
BIOGRAPHY: SI-LAN CHEN LEYDA
Si-Lan Chen was born in Trinidad and moved to London in 1912 where she studied dance at the Stedman Academy. In 1926 she joined her father, who had become secretary for Sun Yat-sen and Foreign Minister of the Canton government. In 1927, after Chiang Kai-shek took power, the family fled to Moscow. Chen enrolled in the Bolshoi Ballet School but disliked the discipline and switched to Vera Maya's school. She gave her first important recital in 1930 at the Moscow Conservatory. After adapting her style to reflect a proletarian ideology, she was proclaimed the first modern Soviet dancer. Throughout the late 1930s and early 1940s she toured the U.S., Mexico and the West Indies performing in benefits for China relief. In the mid-1940s Chen worked in Hollywood as a choreographer, dance instructor and occasionally appeared on film. Her career was complicated by her long struggle to obtain U.S. citizenship. Chen's biography, Footnote to History, was published in 1984.
JAY LEYDA: SELECTED BIBLIOGRAPHY
I. Books by Leyda
1951: The Melville log; a documentary life of Herman Melville, 1819-1891. New York: Harcourt, Brace.
1956: Sergei Rachmaninoff, a lifetime in music, by Sergei Bertensson and Jay Leyda. New York: New York University Press.
1960: Kino, a History of the Russian and Soviet film. New York: Macmillan.
1960: The years and hours of Emily Dickinson. New Haven: Yale University Press.
1964: Films Beget Films: a Study of the Compilation Film. New York: Hill and Wang.
1972: Dianying (Electric Shadows): an Account of Films and the Film audience in China. Cambridge: MIT Press.
1980: Eisenstein at Work. With Zina Voynow and the help of the Eisenstein Committee (Moscow). New York: Pantheon Books and the Museum of Modern Art, 1980.
II. Books edited and/or translated by Leyda
1942: Sergei Eisenstein. The Film Sense. Edited & translated by Leyda. New York: Harcourt Brace.
1947: The Musorgsky reader; a life of Modest Petrovich Musorgsky in letters and documents, edited and translated by Jay Leyda and Sergei Bertensson. New York: W. W. Norton.
1949: Sergei Eisenstein. Film Form: Essays in Film Theory. Edited & translated by Leyda. New York: Harcourt Brace.
1949: The complete stories of Herman Melville. New York: Random House
1952: The portable Melville. New York: Viking Press.
1964: Robert Flaherty. Edited by Leyda and Wolfgang Klaue. Berlin: Henschelverlag. Includes Leyda's essay, "Das Flaherty-Erbe," pp. 46-49.
1968: Sergei Eisenstein. Film Essays, with a Lecture. Edited & translated by Leyda. London: Dennis Dobson. Includes Leyda's "The Published Writings (1922-1964) of Sergei Eisenstein, with notes on their English translations," pp. 188-215.
1969: Vladimir Nizhny. Lessons with Eisenstein. Edited & translated by Leyda and Ivor Montagu. New York: Hill and Hang.
1974: Sergei Eisenstein. Three Films. Edited by Leyda, translated by Diana Matias. New York: Harper & Row. Annotated scripts of Battleship Potemkin, October, and Alexander Nevsky.
1977: Voices of Film Experience: 1894 to the Present. Edited by Leyda, research by Doug Tomlinson and John Hagan. New York: Macmillan.
Sources:
See also Jay Leyda: a life's work (1988), which includes a chronology and bibliography - a copy is in box one, in the first folder.
Scope and Content Note
The collection primarily consists of the papers of Jay Leyda. The collection includes biographical materials on Leyda, his correspondence, and papers pertaining to his work in Chinese and Russian cinema, as well as his jobs as a curator and educator. To a lesser extent, the collection also contains the papers of Jay Leyda's wife, Si-Lan Chen Leyda, and photographs and graphic materials of the Leydas in their personal and professional lives.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into three series. Folders are generally arranged alphabetically.
Series I: Jay Leyda Papers
Subseries A. Biographical
Subseries B. Correspondence
Sub-subseries 1: Alphabetical
Sub-subseries 2: Chronological
Subseries C. Chinese Cinema
Subseries D. Soviet Cinema
Subseries E. Other Projects
Series II: Si-Lan Chen Leyda Papers
Subseries A. Biographical
Subseries B. Correspondence
Subseries C. Dance and Other Activities
Subseries D. Writings
Series III: Photographs and Graphic Materials
Related Archival Materials
Additional Jay Leyda papers can be found at the Museum of Modern Art in New York and at the Department of Special Collections at the University of California, Los Angeles.
Documentary films; Drawings (visual works); Graphic arts; Motion Pictures -- History; Government records; Drafts (documents); Clippings (information artifacts); Motion Pictures -- Editing; Film historians; Documentary films -- History and criticism; Diaries; Motion Pictures -- Soviet Union -- History; Motion Pictures -- China -- History; Correspondence.; Communism and motion pictures -- China; Communism and motion pictures -- Soviet Union; Photographs.; Watercolors (paintings); Typescripts; Manuscripts for publication.; Chen family; Barr, Alfred H., Jr., 1902-1981; Agee, James, 1909-1955; Bowles, Paul, 1910-1999; Benjamin, Walter, 1892-1940; Leyda family; Buñuel, Luis, 1900-1983; Cartier-Bresson, Henri, 1908-2004; Museum of Modern Art (New York, N.Y.). Film Library; Copland, Aaron, 1900-1990; Dickinson, Emily, 1830-1886; Melville, Herman, 1819-1891; Eisenstein, Sergei, 1898-1948; Leyda, Jay, 1910-1988
- Series I: Jay Leyda Papers, 464819
  Scope and Content Note
  This series includes biographical materials on Jay Leyda, his correspondence, and papers pertaining to his work in Chinese and Russian cinema, as well as his jobs as a curator and educator.
  - Subseries A: Biographical / Memorabilia, 80605
    Subseries A: Biographical/Memorabilia includes Leyda's early school records, writings, autobiographical notes and clippings, contracts, awards and documents, membership cards and credentials to the Film and Photo League and the Mosfilms studios. Note: Leyda's parent's marriage certificate, box 1, folder 11A, was repaired (conservation request# 11-205)
    - Jay Leyda: A Life's Work (34 pp.) / Elena Pinto Simon and David Stirk, 1988; 80629 (Box 1, Folder 0.1)
      General
      A biographical and bibliographical monography accompanying a 1988 exhibition at New York University's Photography Department Gallery, Tisch School of the Arts.
    - American Labor Party - Alternate to Judicial District Convention, 1941; 80628 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Army experiences, discharge papers, 1944; 80627 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Autobiographical clippings, 1934-1965; 80626 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Autobiographical notes; 1933-70s, 1933-1979; 80625 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Boyer Galleries brochure - for Emma Lu Davis exhibit, 1937; 80624 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Drawings, undated; 80623 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Early works - poems; c.1925-32, ca.1925-1932; 80622 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - League for Mutual Aid - 20th Anniversary Dinner Program, 1940; 80621 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Membership cards: Film Forum, Workers' Film Photo League, 1933; 80620 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Membership, identification cards; c.1960-c.70s, ca.1960-1979; 80619 (Box 1, Folder 9A)
    - Middlebury College Commencement Exercises Program - Leyda's honorary doctoral degree, 1981; 80618 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Parents' divorce decree, 1913; 80617 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Parents' Marriage Certificate (Margaret Eleanor Leyda and John Jay Flynn)., Mar 7, 1909; 389182 (Box 1, Folder 11A)
    - Participation in exhibition, galleries, 1980; 80616 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Passenger list, SS American Merchant, London to New York, 1936; 80615 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Passport issues, 1955-1956; 80614 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Problems of Portraiture (exhibition catalog - Leyda acknowledged p. 26), 1937; 80613 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Resume, chronology, bibliography of Jay Leyda; c. 1970-86, ca.1970-1986; 80612 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Russian identification cards, other Russian documents, 1934-1937; 80611 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Schoolwork, 1926-1928; 80610 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Sunday school clippings etc., 1916-1920; 80609 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Theatre Library Association Award (for Eisenstein at Work), 1983; 80608 (Box 1, Folder 20)
    - Society of Motion Picture & Television Engineers - Eastman Kodak Gold Medal Award, 1984; 80607 (Box 1, Folder 21)
    - University Film Study Center Newsletter, 1971; 80606 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Subseries B: Correspondence, 80251
    Subseries B: Correspondence contains two sub-subseries: alphabetical and chronological. Leyda's earliest professional mentors Ralph Steiner and Julian Levy are included with his Dayton friends, dancer Josephine Schwarz and artist Jack Rau. Lincoln Kirstein is a lifelong correspondent of Leyda's along with his sister Mina Curtiss. Leyda's connection with the Museum of Modern Art began long before he was hired there, and is evidenced in his correspondence with Alfred Barr and members of the Rockefeller family. There is also a thick MOMA correspondence file. His early liaison with activist attorney Carol King brought him in contact with the likes of Joseph and Charmian Freeman, and his involvement in founding the Film and Photo League introduced him to Romana Javitz of the New York Public Library's circulating picture collection. Most of the era's literary and film world personalities corresponded with Jay at one time or another. Important and/or frequent correspondents include: James Agee, Walter Benjamin, Paul Bowles, Luis Bunuel, Henri Cartier-Bresson, Aaron Copeland, Joseph Cornell, Walker Evans, Helga Greene, Langston Hughes, Joris Ivens, Paul Jarrico, Elia Kazan, Carol King, Naum Kleiman, Fritz Lang, Joseph Losey, Albert Maltz, Ivor Montagu, Man Ray, Satyajit Ray, Abby Rockefeller, Muriel Rukeyser, Georges Sadoul, Gilbert Seldes, Marie Seton, Lee Strasberg, Thornton Wilder, and Edmund Wilson. Also included is Leyda's correspondence with his family, including his mother, Margaret Smith, grandmother Margaret Leyda, maternal aunts Mary and Josephine Leyda, and his half sister Jane Smith and her family.
    - Sub-subseries 1: Alphabetical, 80317
      - Abbott, Bernice, 1970; 80604 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      - Adams, Ansel, undated; 80603 (Box 2, Folder 2)
      - Adler, Stella, 1934; 80602 (Box 2, Folder 3)
      - Agee, James, 1941-1979; 80601 (Box 2, Folder 4)
      - Agha, Dr. M. F. - Conde-Nast Publs., Inc., 1939; 80600 (Box 2, Folder 5)
      - Albera, Francois, 1975; 80599 (Box 2, Folder 6)
      - Alexeieff, Alexandre & Claire, 1943-1980; 80598 (Box 2, Folder 7)
      - Anderson, Emily, 1961; 80597 (Box 2, Folder 8)
      - Andreykov, Todor - Bulgaria National Film Archive, 1978-1979; 80596 (Box 2, Folder 9)
      - Anikst, Dr. Alexander (USSR), 1962-1978; 80595 (Box 2, Folder 10)
      - Aranda, J. F., 1959-1967; 80594 (Box 2, Folder 11)
      - Arensberg, Walter, 1944; 80593 (Box 2, Folder 12)
      - Aristarco, Guido, 1978-1980; 80592 (Box 2, Folder 13)
      - Arnheim, Rudolph, 1971; 80591 (Box 2, Folder 14)
      - Aschaffenburg, Walter, 1954-1959; 80590 (Box 2, Folder 15)
      - Aschaffenburg, Walter, 1960-1965; 80589 (Box 2, Folder 16)
      - Aschaffenburg, Walter, 1966-1980; 80588 (Box 2, Folder 17)
      - Attasheva, Pera, 1937-1965; 80587 (Box 2, Folder 18)
      - Auden, W. H., undated; 80586 (Box 2, Folder 19)
      - Averill, Sue - Re: Wu Tian Ming, 1985; 80585 (Box 2, Folder 20)
      - Baldwin, James; c. 1960s, ca.1960-1969; 80584 (Box 2, Folder 21)
      - Barna, Ion, 1964-1966; 80583 (Box 2, Folder 22)
      - Barna, Ion, 1967-1979; 80582 (Box 2, Folder 23)
      - Barnour, Eric, 1970-1980; 80581 (Box 2, Folder 24)
      - Barr, Alfred & Marga, 1928-1986; 80580 (Box 2, Folder 25)
      - Bartos, Celeste, 1977-1979; 80579 (Box 2, Folder 26)
      - Baskin, Leonard & Esther, 1957-1958; 80578 (Box 2, Folder 27)
      - Baxandall, Lee, 1963-1967; 80577 (Box 2, Folder 28)
      - Bennet, William R. - Bio of Modeste Musorgsky, 1980; 80576 (Box 2, Folder 29)
      - Benjamin, Walter, 1937; 80575 (Box 2, Folder 30)
      - Bernstein, David, 1937-1938; 80574 (Box 2, Folder 31)
      - Bernstein, Sidney, 1935-1956; 80573 (Box 2, Folder 32)
      - Bessie, Alvah, 1944-1979; 80572 (Box 2, Folder 33)
      - Bertensson, Serge (Will), 1945; 80571 (Box 2, Folder 34)
      - James Beveridge Associates, 1978-1979; 80570 (Box 2, Folder 35)
      - Biberman, Herbert, 1962-1963; 80569 (Box 2, Folder 36)
      - Bill, Katharine; 1933?, ca.1933; 80568 (Box 2, Folder 37)
      - Binder, Pearl, 1935-1938; 80567 (Box 2, Folder 38)
      - Bingham, Millicent, 1956; 80566 (Box 2, Folder 39)
      - Black, Helen, 1942-1969; 80565 (Box 2, Folder 40)
      - Bourke-White, Margaret, 1932; 80564 (Box 2, Folder 41)
      - Boyajian, Aran & Boyajian-Starr, Cecile, 1962-1982; 80563 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      - Bowles, Paul, 1939-1945; 80562 (Box 3, Folder 2)
      - Bowser, Eileen, 1964-1979; 80561 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      - Brandon, Thomas J., 1959-1979; 80560 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      - Brown, Richard, 1943; 80559 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      - Brownlow, Kevin, 1972-1973; 80558 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      - Bunuel, Luis, 1940-1966; 80557 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      - Burliuk, David, 1942; 80556 (Box 3, Folder 8)
      - Burstein, Joseph, undated; 80555 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      - Callenbach, Ernest, 1964-1980; 80554 (Box 3, Folder 10)
      - Capra, Frank, 1943; 80553 (Box 3, Folder 11)
      - Cartier-Bresson, Henri, 1938-1946; 80552 (Box 3, Folder 12)
      - Carynnyk, Marco, 1970-1973; 80551 (Box 3, Folder 13)
      - Caspary, Vera, undated; 80550 (Box 3, Folder 14)
      - Catling, D.C., 1935; 80549 (Box 3, Folder 15)
      - Cavalcanti, A., 1958-1977; 80548 (Box 3, Folder 16)
      - Chiarini, Luigi, 1949-1967; 80547 (Box 3, Folder 17)
      - Christie, Ian - British Film Institute, 1987; 80546 (Box 3, Folder 18)
      - Clurman, Harold; c. 1934-44, ca.1934-1944; 80545 (Box 3, Folder 19)
      - Cohen, Bernard - "The First Explanation of Interference" (incsribed offprint), 1940; 80544 (Box 3, Folder 20)
      - Collins, Frances, 1939-1983; 80543 (Box 3, Folder 21)
      - Copland, Aaron, 1935-1948; 80542 (Box 3, Folder 22)
      - Cornell, Joseph, 1935-1953; 80541 (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - Craig, G., 1935; 80540 (Box 3, Folder 24)
      - Cunard, Nancy; 1930s, 1930-1939; 80539 (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Curtiss, Mina, 1950-1971; 80538 (Box 3, Folder 26)
      - DeAntonio, Emile, 1968-1972; 80537 (Box 3, Folder 27)
      - Disney, Roy, 1985; 80536 (Box 3, Folder 28)
      - Dudley, Jane; c.1940?, ca.1940; 80535 (Box 3, Folder 29)
      - Dykson, Ruth, 1930-1935; 80534 (Box 3, Folder 30)
      - Elton, Arthur & Margaret, 1961-1966; 80533 (Box 3, Folder 31)
      - Evans, Ernestine; 1930s-67, ca.1930-1967; 80532 (Box 3, Folder 32)
      - Evans, Walker, 1933-1973; 80531 (Box 3, Folder 33)
      - Flaherty, Frances & David, 1965-1969; 80530 (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Francis, David, 1963; 80529 (Box 3, Folder 35)
      - Franklin, Leonard & Cole Publishers (A.M. Krich), 1946; 80528 (Box 3, Folder 36)
      - Freeman, Joseph & Lee Lowenfish, 1932-1980; 80527 (Box 3, Folder 37)
      - Frida, Myrtil, 1966-1967; 80526 (Box 3, Folder 38)
      - Frost, Ed, 1984; 80525 (Box 3, Folder 39)
      - Geduld, Harry M., 1970; 80524 (Box 4, Folder 1)
      - Glenny, Michael, 1979; 80523 (Box 4, Folder 2)
      - Goberman, Max, undated; 80522 (Box 4, Folder 3)
      - Godfrey; [1957], ca.1957; 80521 (Box 4, Folder 4)
      - Gordian Press, 1967-1977; 80520 (Box 4, Folder 5)
      - Gray, Camilla, 1964-1969; 80519 (Box 4, Folder 6)
      - Greene, Helga (Helga Greene Literary Agency), 1956-1966; 80518 (Box 4, Folder 7)
      - Greene, Helga (Helga Greene Literary Agency), 1967-1985; 80517 (Box 4, Folder 8)
      - Griffith, Richard, 1958-1969; 80516 (Box 4, Folder 9)
      - George, George, 1944-1984; 80515 (Box 4, Folder 10)
      - Gregor, Ulrich, 1966-1968; 80514 (Box 4, Folder 11)
      - Grieg, Nordahl, undated; 80513 (Box 4, Folder 12)
      - Grierson, John, 1940-1968; 80512 (Box 4, Folder 13)
      - Hackett, Blanche, 1977-1985; 80511 (Box 4, Folder 14)
      - Hammond, John; [1945], ca.1945; 80510 (Box 4, Folder 15)
      - Harcourt, Brace & Co. Publishers, 1942-1972; 80509 (Box 4, Folder 16)
      - Harvard Press, 1958-1986; 80508 (Box 4, Folder 17)
      - Heartfield, John & Gertrude, 1965-1969; 80507 (Box 4, Folder 18)
      - Heym, Stefan, 1969; 80506 (Box 4, Folder 19)
      - Hill, Steven, 1965-1987; 80505 (Box 4, Folder 20)
      - Hoffman, Irving, 1940; 80504 (Box 4, Folder 21)
      - Hallis, Ron, 1984; 80503 (Box 4, Folder 22)
      - Hoskins, Marvin; [1975], ca.1975; 80502 (Box 4, Folder 23)
      - Houghton, Norris, 1962-1970; 80501 (Box 4, Folder 24)
      - Howard, Leon, 1964-1968; 80500 (Box 4, Folder 25)
      - Howard, Sidney (Film Forum), 1933; 80499 (Box 4, Folder 26)
      - Hubley, John, 1975-1977; 80498 (Box 4, Folder 27)
      - Hudyma, J. P., 1946; 80497 (Box 4, Folder 28)
      - Hughes, Langston, 1942; 80496 (Box 4, Folder 29)
      - Isaacs, Edith (Theatre Arts Monthly), 1933-1946; 80495 (Box 4, Folder 30)
      - Isherwood, Christopher, 1966; 80494 (Box 4, Folder 31)
      - Ivens, Joris & Helen van Dongen-Ivens, 1931-1983; 80493 (Box 4, Folder 32)
      - Iwasaki, Akira, 1970-1972; 80492 (Box 4, Folder 33)
      - Jacobs, Lewis, 1967-1979; 80491 (Box 4, Folder 34)
      - Jaffe, David, 1975-1983; 80490 (Box 4, Folder 35)
      - Jarrico, Paul & Sylvia, 1947-1986; 80489 (Box 4, Folder 36)
      - Javitz, Romana, 1933-1978; 80488 (Box 4, Folder 37)
      - Jensen, Karl; 1930-[35], 1930-1935; 80487 (Box 4, Folder 38)